<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessed works of the light of God's holy and blessed spirit exalted above the works of darkness with some informations how to escape out of sin and iniquity, and a clear way discovered into the truth : with a short testimony of the cry of Babylon's merchants by reason of the day that is coming upon them / [by] Stephen Smith.</title>
            <author>Smith, Stephen, 1623-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60558</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37568</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16974420</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16974420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60558)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessed works of the light of God's holy and blessed spirit exalted above the works of darkness with some informations how to escape out of sin and iniquity, and a clear way discovered into the truth : with a short testimony of the cry of Babylon's merchants by reason of the day that is coming upon them / [by] Stephen Smith.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Stephen, 1623-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
               <term>Inner Light.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105580:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Bleſſed Works OF THE Light of God's Holy and BLESSED SPIRIT Exalted above the Works of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>With ſome Informations how to eſcape out of Sin and Iniquity, and a clear Way diſcovered into the Truth.</p>
            <p>With a ſhort Teſtimony of the Cry of <hi>Babylons</hi>'s Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants by reaſon of the Day that is coming upon them.</p>
            <p>Stephen Smith</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2</hi> Peter <hi>3.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl> Looking for and haſting unto the Coming of the Day of God, wherein the Heavens being on Fire ſhall be diſſolved and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent Heat; nevertheleſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Promiſe, we look for new Heavens and new Earth wherein dwells Righteouſneſs.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1673.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105580:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105580:2"/>
            <head>THE Bleſſed Works OF THE Light of God's Holy and BLESSED SPIRIT Exalted above the Works of Darkneſs</head>
            <p>COme, ſit down together in a deep Silence out of all Fleſhly Wiſdom, forgiving all Treſpaſſes, that he that ſits upon his Throne, who ſaid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I make all things new, that he may forgive all your Treſpaſſes; and then wait for Acception into God's Pure Holy Covenant, his Holy Law in the Mind that it may be writ in the Heart, and they ſhall not teach every man his Neighbour and every Man his Brother, ſaying, know the Lord; for all ſhall know me from the leaſt to the greateſt; for I will be merciful to their Unrighteouſneſs, and their Sins and Iniquities will I remember no more; a bleſſed day, magnified be the Lord, whoſe Works praiſe him forever (and not good Words out of wicked Workers Mouthes) ſo theſe mighty Works of the mighty God, the which he is working and bringing to paſs through his mighty Power, are appointed that Mankind ſhould live in the Enjoyment of them, to the Praiſe and Honour of his Maker forever.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:105580:3"/>
            <p> And that it may be diſtinguiſhed between Evil Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers who have got the good Words, and the good Works from whence all true, and good and gratious Words came, (obſerve).</p>
            <p>In one of the Collects appointed in the Book of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer</hi> it is thus written,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Almighty and Everlaſting God, which of thy tender Love towards Man, hath ſent our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt to take upon him our Fleſh, and to ſuffer Death upon the Croſs, that all Man-kind ſhould follow the Example of his great Humility, mercifully grant that we both follow the Example of his Patience and be made Partakers of his Reſurrection, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now mind, To pray for this, that is common, and uſed in the old World of Tranſgreſſion, where Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Sin is, which ſeparates from God, and are out of his Bleſſed Works: But to be in the Humility and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, this is God's Work, where his Will is done on Earth as it is in Heaven: So that if People would but ſo far condiſcend to the Will of God, as to ſit down in Coolneſs in a true Silence of all the Works of the fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom, would they not agree with us, who are in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in Judgment at leaſt, though it may be not in Practice, <hi>viz. That Words without Effects are as Dreams and Chaff</hi> (to the Wheat, the Subſtance) So he that hath a Dream, let him tell his Dream; but he that hath God's Word let him ſpeak it: What is the Chaff to the Wheat? <hi>Is not my Word like a Fire,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and like a Hammer, that breaketh the Rock in pieces,</hi> Jer. 23. <hi>I am againſt the Prophet,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>that ſteals my Word from his Neighbour, who uſe their Tongues, &amp; ſay, he ſaith, and propheſie falſe Dreams, and tell them, and cauſe people to Err by their Lyes and Lightneſs.</hi> And ſo now in Coolneſs, when the Works of the Enemy are down,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105580:3"/>viz. Prejudice, and Paſſion, &amp;c. then by a little Work of God, in its leaſt Appearance, by which Mankind is made ſenſible, they may ſee by this ſmall Diſtinction what it is that we, who are in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſtand for (and againſt) And when the Eye of your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is opened, to behold his Glorious Works whom you have pierced, then will you love us, whom ſo many have hated, becauſe of our Teſtimony of God's Works. Do but ſee how you firſt hated the Light of God in your ſelves, before that great Darkneſs came o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you to hate us, who are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe we are bowed unto Chriſt's Spirit, the true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Spirit, and therein have in ſome meaſure partaken of his Cup, out of which ſome indeed have drunk very deep, even to the following of his great Humility and Patience, even to Death, as in <hi>New-England Sufferings</hi> may be ſeen (by thoſe cruel imaginary <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whoſe wicked Hands have been deep in the ſhedding of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Blood. And though through Ignorance the Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of God's People hath been much in Old <hi>England,</hi> yet they have not been in that deſperate kind as there; where out of doubt they are more drunk with the Whore's Cup of Sorceries &amp; Witchcraft, then thoſe of that kind are here in old <hi>England,</hi> whoſe ſpirit is felt; but that their Wings are cut, ſo cannot fly at that rate, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they would be at; for now their Hands are tied, how wonderfully do their Tongues go? by which its plain they have no Bridle, but are ſet on Fire of Hell, Wondering, Deſpiſing and Fretting againſt the Work of the Lord in this the Day of his Power, though Thouſands are raiſed by it, to declare and publiſh the ſame in Words, in Life and Converſation, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And now you Vain and Empty Profeſſors and Notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105580:4"/>who are ſaying in your Dark and Imaginary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivings of things, That if you had been in the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> dayes, thoſe learned Rabbies, you would not have done ſo wickedly as to Crucifie the Juſt, and call for his Blood to be upon your Heads. But come, hearken in the Cool; Did not thoſe <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſay the like of their Fathers, who Stoned and Killed the Prophets whom God ſent in Love to them? And were not they in a worſe Practice (though they ſpoak other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes?) And was not the Cauſe of their Blindneſs from reſiſting God's Works in his Spirit, by which means they had no Revelation there of the things of God, notwithſtanding they had the Scriptures without, which teſtified of him; yet they being ſo Wicked to put out the Candle that ſhould have lighted them in it, they ſaw not the Subſtance ſpoken of in the Scriptures, were more darkned, judging by that Law that Chriſt was a Devil, and a Deceiver, and ſo ought to dye, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any regard to his Innocent Holy Life, and his great Humility and Patience: But though they crucified him, yet they could not ſo bury him but that he riſe again, and appeared in divers manners; and after he was riſen opened the Scriptures to his Followers, who loved Him.</p>
            <p>Therefore Profeſſors of Works without, who are not Poſſeſſors of God's Bleſſed Holy Works within; What though you do ſay, If you had been in your Fathers the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> dayes, you would not have done as they did: But come, be patient a little; the Works of Truth have a good Tendency, though they be bitter to the Guilty for the Preſent; come, I ſay, look where you are; by the Light you may ſee; you muſt ſee by it at laſt; it were better for you if you would let your Eye be opened now, and ſee that offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105580:4"/>Eye pulled out which hath been offended at God's Works all this while: So do not harden your Hearts in this Day of God's Power being manifeſt, leſt you be cut off from his Reſt forever. Come therefore you that are judging others that did wickedly in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, by reſiſting God's holy Spirit, ſo had none of the Works of its Revelation; come ſee now what La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude your Works are under; If you be in the ſame Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in the Fleſh as they were in, its no matter what you ſay: Come now to the Tryal; What Experience have you of the Operation of God's Spirit? How much of the Mind and Will of God hath it revealed to you? Can you ſay, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> by the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Knowledge of the Revelation of God's holy Spirit? Or have you only talkt of it, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did, who ſaid, <hi>We have God for our Father,</hi> when they were doing the Devil's Works? Come do not ſtop your Ears; Have you heard the Voice of God or ſeen his Shape? or are you ignorant of it, as they were who accuſed Chriſt, as if he was bearing Falſe Witneſs? Nay, come fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Have you not ſaid, <hi>That Revelations are ceaſed,</hi> and thereby ſhut up the Way to the Kingdom of God, and from the Knowledge of his Righteouſneſs by your wicked Works, in going about to eſtabliſh your own Righteouſneſs, and Works therein for term of life.</p>
            <p>Come you that have ſet up the Law and Covenant without (above the Law and Covenant within; are not theſe your own Works? and have not they made you as blind as your Fathers, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> that you can neither ſee nor hear?) but in your blind Zeal are perſecuting Chriſt's near Relations, who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in their Generation, even by the Drawings of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105580:5"/>his Father's Spirit unto his Humility and Patience, who is the Way, in whom God's Will was done: And did not Chriſt give Teſtimony of his Relations, his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Brothers and Siſters, who did his Father's Will? And is not this to be done on Earth? And is it not the Will of God that we ſhould ſpeak the Truth at all times, and that we ſhould be led and guided by the Spirit of Truth into all Truth? (is there any Sin in the Guide:) And is not this Chriſt of God the ſame Auointing or Teacher, as he was in the beginning of the World? Was not he before <hi>Abraham</hi> was? And is not he the ſame yeſterday, to day and forever, as he was in the beginning, who was <hi>David</hi>'s Lord, and the Holy Men's Lord in all Ages? And is not he the Covenant by which all muſt come unto God? Was he not given for a Covenant, and a Light to enlighten people, and to be their Salvation, to lead and command his People? And muſt not his Sheep hear his Voice? And is not he the ſame that he was in the beginning? And is not this the Precious and Tryed Stone, which the wiſe Builders, building without, are confounded and ſtumble at, even the higheſt Notioniſts in the fleſhly Wiſdom, in their higheſt Conceivings about the Holy Men's Words? Come, examine your ſelves, and ſee whether Chriſt be not in you, except you be Reprobates: You Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, how hath the Godd of the World led you about, and blinded you, that you cannot ſee the Light of this Glorious Goſpel? Come ſee the Cauſe; Have you not been making Proviſion for the Fleſh in the firſt place, and anſwering the Luſts thereof after the Glory of the old World of Sin and Iniquity? Hath not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Perſons been in your Eye, and Filthy Lucre,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105580:5"/>and Praiſe of Men, and Greeting in Market-Places? Have you not preacht and prayed in your own Wills, and run for Gifts and Rewards in your own Wills? And is not all this Honour to be had below? And have you not ſought it before the Honour of God's Work in your Hearts? And is not this the Cauſe of your Ignorance of God's Kingdom, and his Righteouſneſs (Chriſt) and his Relations, his Mother, Siſters and Brethren, who are ſanctified and bleſt by the Will of God, where it is done in Truth and Righteouſneſs? and where that is done, do not ſuch only confirm in Truth and Reallity all God's bleſſed and holy Works without in all Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? So do not envy and hate the People called <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> for maintaining the Works of God's holy Spirit within them; for there are many of them have been as high Talkers of the Works of God in holy Men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, as you are; but found not ſuch Salvation, as to venture Souls, and Bodies and Eſtates, till we came to ceaſe from our own Labours in our own Willings and Runnings; and ſo our Hearts were bowed unto <hi>God's holy Will</hi> in the deep Silence of all Fleſhly Reaſonings and Conſultations: So by the Works of God's holy and bleſſed Spirit the Way of God came to be made manifeſt in us; the which is a Pure, Holy, Undefiled Way, Chriſt, the ſame yeſterday, to day and forever, as he was in the beginning without Guile, without Sin; no Iniquity is in him; he that is the Hope of Glory, the great My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery made manifeſt in us <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who in former times, when without the Knowledge of him in the World, had Lords many, and Maſters many, and feigned Faiths and Beliefs concerning him many and divers: But when we were given up clearly to ſeek the Kingdom of God, without any reſerve of making Proviſion for the Fleſh,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105580:6"/>then the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> God's Building, came down from above, the Mother of all the Faithful, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no Evil can be conceived, whoſe Children in her are made free from the Law of Sin and Death; and this bleſſed City hath no need of the Sun, neither of the Moon to ſhine in it; for the Glory of God doth lighten it, and the Lamb is the Light thereof. This bleſſed Habitation is prepared for God's People, who love the Light of his Appearance, and delight to do his Will.</p>
            <p>So away with all Falſe Accuſations from all you Falſe Accuſers of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who ſay, <hi>We ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be Saved by a Righteouſneſs of our own, and by Works of our own:</hi> If it were ſo, as you falſely and vainly do ſay, then might we not keep in the Broad Way, with you Hypocrites, who are gotten above the daily Croſs, and ſo led about by the Thief above the Door, where you Foxes, who are cunning in Hunting about after o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Works, have Holes enough to creep and cring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to keep you in the Glory of the World of Sin and Iniquity, where you have had a long Trade in your I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations, conceiving God's Works in his bleſſed Inſtruments without you, whoſe Lines you have long made your boaſt of; ſo your Lyes are upon your own Heads. For, this I teſtifie, and the Teſtimony is the ſame in Thouſands, who are Witneſſes of the Works of God's holy Spirit, in ſome Degree or Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is in Chriſt, God's Covenant, in which we hope for Salvation, and in no Covenant nor Work of Man's; and in this Covenant we are made a good Savour unto God, and one unto another: And Acceptance with God is obtained no other way but by the one pure Offering, without Spot or Blemiſh, by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105580:6"/>the effectual Workings of the Eternal Spirit, where the Blood of Chriſt is witneſſed to be ſufficient to purge Conſciences of dead Works, and ſo to ſerve God in the New and Living Way, which he hath conſecrated for us through the Vail, his Fleſh: And therefore all who are thus Partakers of God's Works, by the Revelation of God's Spirit, being true Witneſſes of the Bleſſing of God in this one Unſpotted Offering, we cannot but confeſs him before Men; denying all imaginary Offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in mens wills, where their Garments are filled with Spots and Blemiſhes, and their Conſciences are defiled with dead Works of their own Inventions and Works, the which having ſome outward Shew of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs may Recommend unto Man, who lives in the ſame, but not unto God; and therefore Experience in the Works of God's bleſſed Spirit hath taught us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them.</p>
            <p>And by this Chriſt of God, the Mediator of the New Covenant, we have Acceptance with God, from whence the Knowledge of Salvation comes, by the Remiſſion of Offences and Sins; and therefore we deny all falſe and vain Mediatorſhip of vain man in his vain VVorks of Conceivings &amp; Imaginations concerning this Mediator; the which is really to be enjoyed and known by the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual VVorkings of God's Eternal Spirit, to the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Peace of Souls who partake thereof.</p>
            <p>And through the bleſſed VVorks of this bleſſed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God the Deaf Ear comes to be opened, to hear the Voice of the one true powerful Shepherd, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone doth feed the Sheep of his Paſture with that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and wholſome Food, the which cauſeth Sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart and Mind, and therein doth he take Care to preſerve and keep his Sheep in a living Senſe of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105580:7"/>Love &amp; Fatherly Care, who calls to his Sheep when the Lion, the VVolf and the Bear appears, and ſtrengtheneth them who take Pleaſure in hearkening and obeying his Voice. So to the one Shepherd and one Fold Teſtimony is given, unto whom all that are erred and ſtrayed muſt return, if ever they witneſs Deliverance from Evil and Preſervation from Danger. So we deny all falſe Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds whoſe VVorks of Darkneſs tend to the ſcattering people in their Minds and Underſtandings from the Senſe of God's VVorks in Chriſt, in reconciling loſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and bringing them home unto himſelf (the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all) of which the Law outward was but a Shadow of good things the which are injoyed in this one Shepherd and Biſhop, who takes Care and Overſight of Souls; magnified and praiſed be his holy and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous VVorks of Redemprion forever and ever.</p>
            <p>And ſo to the Honour of this one bleſſed Phyſitian of Souls, whoſe <hi>Works are certain</hi> and <hi>effectual,</hi> the which has been tryed by many wounded Souls, who could find no Cure without by the fooliſh and vain Phyſitians without, who are meer Deceivers, and Daubers up of people through their Inchantments and Sorceries, by which they have made a long Prey of people through their fair Speeches, getting their Money through meer De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and Flattery, intruding into things they have no Knowledge of, in which VVorks they are pufft up above the pure holy VVorks of God's bleſſed Spirit, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of which they have denyed, they in lew there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have ſet up their own Imaginations and Conceivings in the Revelation of their Singular exalted Spirit, the Flattery and Deceit of which having taken with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, how are Nations corrupted by it? and what Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry have theſe wicked VVorks brought into this Nation?
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105580:7"/>God having given ſignal Teſtimonies of Diſlike unto them by Sword, Plague, Fire and Sword, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Meſſengers whom he hath drawn near unto himſelf by his VVorks, by the hands of them Meſſengers hath he ſent VVarning upon VVarning, and Exhortation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Exhortation, with tenders of his Bleſſed VVorks of Reconciliation upon juſt and equal terms, of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies repenting, and turning unto him by turning from their Wickedneſs: But what Entertainment theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Living God have found by theſe fooliſh Phyſitians, who are meer Time-Servers for their own Ends, whoſe Refuge is an Arm of Fleſh to defend their wicked corrupt Works, which have filled the Nations with their Defilements, who by their Flatteries have drawn a Compliance from Magiſtrates, to puniſh the Meſſengers and Servants of the Moſt High God for tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Truth from a certain Knowledge of the Works of God's Spirit of Truth, and therein teſtifying againſt the Works of Error and Darkneſs. But the Sufferings that have been for this Love of God in and through them who have been Inſtruments in his hands, may through ſearch be known; ſo Teſtimony is given againſt them, who are in the Exaltation of Works without, and denying the immediate bleſſed Works of God's ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit in its Operations and Revelations of the Mind and Will of God unto wounded Souls within.</p>
            <p>And further concerning theſe Bleſſed Works of God's Righteous Holy Spirit, the which are attended with Peace, unto which Way many have been turned; and becauſe ſome loiter, and are ſloathful, and yet remain unconverted of the Old Man's corrupt Words and Deeds, and therefore not fit to put on the New Man, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105580:8"/>and ſome who were in the Way, do turn out of it again; and ſome fall head-long down to Perdition: Oh! what Occaſion hath the Watchers for Evil ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at this, and thereby ſet at nought God's Works in his Holy Righteous Spirit, and them that abide therein, making Concluſions in their dark imaginary Concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings of the Works of God, <hi>That he hath no ſuch perfect Works now adayes; but that all are fallible and changeable:</hi> and ſo meaſure and weigh the things of God in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt falſe Meaſure and Ballance, which things are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination in the Sight of God. So Teſtimony is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to God's bleſſed Works, though many are ſo brittle that they will not abide them; yet notwithſtanding God's Works in and through his holy Spirit of Truth are Righteous, Holy, Perfect in every Degree and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and remains firm in Goodneſs and unchangeable, there being no Spot nor Blemiſh in them, the which prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes him forever, out of which none ſhall ever find Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of him. Mutter, Peep, Whine and Scold as long as you will, your Works of Darkneſs muſt down, which have corrupted the Nations, which is the Cauſe of the great Judgments paſt in this Nation, and the greater yet to come: For the Sword of the Spirit, the Word of God, is gone out againſt wicked Workers and works, and thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>No Peace to the Wicked; their Prayers are Abomination in my Sight.</hi> So whatſoever your Profeſſions and Coverings therein be, of your Talkings and Imaginations concerning the Gift of God, which is Life Eternal, you being really out of it, in your own imaginary Parts &amp; Gifts, in comprehending the VVorks done without you, and ſo not ſenſible of any Real, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, Pure VVork of God's Holy Spirit in you, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105580:8"/>which is the Cauſe you are ſo Dark, and wickedly Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to plead for Sin, the which is accompanied with the VVages of Death; the Cauſe of Death being Sin, the which remaining, the Effects cannot ceaſe, even Death and Corruption from that venemous Sting over all Fleſh that is corrupted with it. So for Shame leave your falſe Accuſations againſt an Innocent People, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Name of <hi>Quakers,</hi> for teſtifying of the VVorks of God's holy Spirit, the which are perfect in every Degree, and therefore there is not the leaſt Sin nor Evil in them. So all you who ſay, <hi>You are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin in your Beſt Duties;</hi> I ſay, They are all VVorks of your own (which blind and hide God's Works from you.) And as you may read of the Works of God's Spirit in <hi>Mordecai,</hi> how they could not bow to the Pride and Arrogance of <hi>Haman;</hi> and alſo, the Works of God's Spirit in <hi>Daniel,</hi> how they could not bow to them that would have reſtrained and limited them; and alſo the Works of God's Spirit in <hi>Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> how they could not bow to the Golden Image, ſet up by <hi>Nebuchadnezer,</hi> though Laws under Penalties of Death in a Cruel Manner was before them; and alſo, the Works of God's Holy Spirit in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> through the Strength of which they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-went hard and grievous things under the ſpirit of Antichriſt, which got up in a Form of the good Words, in the Pleaſures and Vanities of the Works of the fleſhly Wiſdom, the which have been kept up by the ſame Wiſdom, by an Arm of Fleſh, under which the Innocent People, who are true Witneſſes of the Works of God's Spirit, have ſuffered very deeply in this Age, the which cannot be hid, though the Cauſe for which they have thus ſuffered is ſo far hid that it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105580:9"/>cannot be believed, though they have been wonderfully declared of. But it is <hi>Mordecai, Daniel, Shadrach, Meſhach</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi>'s God which we, who are in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> do worſhip in and by the Effects and bleſſed O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of his own bleſſed Spirit, wherein ſtands our Confidence, and not in Fleſh; and our Faith, Belief and Hope is in him, that he will turn the Hearts of many of our Enemies unto us, though many will periſh in their Gain-ſaying. So over all the VVorks and Powers of Darkneſs is our Faith and Belief, that the Holy Righteous VVorks of God's bleſſed Spirit ſhall be exalted, and the God of Truth in and through his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed VVorks, in preparing and fitting the Hearts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Knowledge of him ſhall encreaſe, till it ſpread over all. And for this Purpoſe hath God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many, contrary to the VViſdom of the VVorld, in whom he hath made known his <hi>Righteous Works,</hi> who have Unity and Fellowſhip therein (who are true La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers therein) purely out of Love to God and his bleſſed VVorks, in Good-will and true Love to all men, that all may taſte of the Goodneſs of God, the Experience of which will bring Mankind to be of one Mind and Heart, and therein to agree to Praiſe and Magnifie God, who ſhows Man his Thoughts, to whom belongs Honour and Glory forever.</p>
            <p>And now all you Leaders of the People, in all Forms and Faſhions, who are denying the Works of the Divine Power of God in its bleſſed Operation and powerful Working, in ſetting free them who are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy laden and weary through the Enemies works of Sin and Iniquity, the which you ſay <hi>cannot be Overcome;</hi> therefore you are Denyers of the Sufficiency of God's
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105580:9"/>Works and his Kingdom, wherein dwells Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Peace and Joy in and through the Effectual Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of God's Holy Spirit, the which, though you ſay in words, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy Will be done, &amp;c.</hi> But being Sayers, and not Doers, you are ſo darkened that with all your own Wills and Mights you are ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening the Old Kingdom of Tranſgreſſion, where Sin and Iniquity aboundeth, the Devil's works: Was it not by reaſon of Tranſgreſſion that the firſt Law, the firſt Covenant, was added, which was written in Tables of Stone? And was not this in Force till the Manifeſtation of the Seed of Life and Power, the Coming of the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> to finiſh Tranſgreſſion, and to put an End to Sin, and ſo bring in everlaſting Righteouſneſs, God's Kingdom?</p>
            <p>Now all you blind Leaders of the Blind, is not here God's Second Covenant, writ in the Heart, into which all muſt come that come unto God, where his Light is to ſhine, who is the <hi>True Light that enlightens every Man that comes into the World?</hi> And if this Righteous Law be taken heed unto, will it not judge Luſt when it riſes in the Heart? And will it not judge Anger when it ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the heart? and will it not judge every Deſire of Breaking Promiſe, when it ariſes in the Heart? And will it not judge every Haſty and Froward Action and Lightneſs, when they appear in the Heart? And is not all that proceeds from this Righteous Law and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God in the Heart Pure Truth, <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay?</hi> And what is more then Plain Truth, <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> is it not judged by this pure Law in the Heart? And are not all forbidden to <hi>Swear</hi> by this one Law-giver, who is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Save or to Deſtroy? And muſt not his Righteous Law and Decree take place, though many Laws through Darkneſs and Ignorance may be made againſt it? And
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105580:10"/>muſt not all that come to <hi>Sion,</hi> the City of the Living God, be Redeemed through theſe Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? And are not the great Mercies of God witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in and through theſe Righteous Judgments? And all that will not come under this Righteous Law and Government, where Mercy and Peace kiſſes, and Truth and Righteouſneſs is ſet over all; is it not juſt that they be left to Judgment without Mercy? So is not Deſtruction from Self-willing and Running of people out of the Counſel and Knowledge of the Will and Mind of the Living God? And is not the Salvation of every Soul in and through the Righteous Decrees and Juſt and Holy Laws of God, which is Light in every Conſcience? And muſt not all that come to Salvation come firſt to the Way and Means that God hath ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? And is not the Second Coming of Chriſt, in the Light of his Holy Spirit, the Way by which all muſt come unto God, the which is without Sin, without Spot, without Guile? And muſt not all that come unto God come unto him in this one Bleſſed Savoury Offering? And is not this Chriſt of God the ſame yeſterday, to day and forever as he was before <hi>Abraham</hi> was, and ſo the ſame in the beginning of all things? And muſt not all that come to God come out of Tranſgreſſion, the Cauſe why Mankind was drove from the Preſence of God? And is not this Chriſt of God the Way out of Tranſgreſſion, who was obedient and ſubject to the Will of his Father in all things? And muſt not they, all that are ſaved, be brought into this bleſſed Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Life, the End of God's great Love in his Son manifeſted to the World, that through him they might not abide and periſh in Darkneſs; but through belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and obeying that Second Coming and Appearance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105580:10"/>of the Light of him, they might have the Light and Underſtanding of the Life of him, the one bleſſed Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, <hi>that perfects forever them that are ſanctified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now all you blind Leaders of the Blind, under all your Imaginary Lifeleſs Confeſſions and Profeſſions of God and Chriſt, what ſtrength of Arguments do you uſe in your perverſe Wills and Affections to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the Old World of Tranſgreſſion in Sin and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whereby you go about with all your Might to make void the Second Covenant, which is without Fault, and ſo you ſhut up the Way to God's Kingdom and the Knowledge of his Righteouſneſs, by labouring and moiling in your vain Service and Works to eſtabliſh your own Righteouſneſs and dark Works therein? And by this Fruitleſs Labour and Travel, what Darkneſs and Blindneſs have you brought over the Nations, through your ignorant Conceivings of thoſe gratious Words, which were ſpoken by the effectual working and moving of God's Holy Spirit in and through Holy Men, the which was for a bleſſed End ſpoken, even to turn peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the Darkneſs, which was over them by reaſon of Tranſgreſſion, unto the true Witneſs in them, the Light that makes manifeſt all that is reprovable and wicked in Mankind, the which being turned from, and the Light obeyed, that they may be led to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, that they may not be without God in the World, <hi>whom to know is Life Eternal?</hi> And ſo Light is ſown for the Righteous, that through this bleſſed Seed the Serpent's Head may be bruiſed, and kept under in all; and ſo is way made to put on the Heavenly Image again, by being led and guided out of Darkneſs by the Light of the <hi>Emanuel,</hi> in and through every bleſſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105580:11"/>and glorious Degree of his Works to the Mark of that Price, the Meaſure and Stature of the Fulneſs of Chriſt Jeſus, the Heavenly Man, the Heavenly Image; <hi>as many as are baptized into Chriſt put on Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſay unto you blind Leaders of the Blind, who have got ſome few of the Gratious Words and Works of the Righteous Men of God; therefore I ſay but few of them, becauſe there is but little upon record of thoſe mighty Works, which did then ſhew forth the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Power of God in and by the effectual Workings of his holy bleſſed Spirit; the which, if all had been written, the World could not have contained the Books; and of that which was written, you have but a part, with which you blind Leaders of the Blind have made a long Trade, in Wreſting, Perverting and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting to your own Deſtruction, making them look every way but the right in your Imaginary Conceivings thereof. So wrong you are in your Judgments, who have denyed the effectual Workings of God's Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that what in you lies by your Works of Darkneſs you are making void God's Holy Law and Covenant, as to any true Underſtanding or Knowledge of it in the Mind and Heart: And ſo building your ſelves up in Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and Conceivings, what Strangers are you to God's Holy Works in and by the effectual Working of his holy Spirit within Man? How brutiſh are you in your Underſtandings, to ſtand and wonder, and ſome to deſpiſe, till they periſh at the News of theſe Works, though God hath raiſed many faithful Witneſſes, who have declared and given Teſtimony to them, even to the laying down their Lives, and many their Liberties, and in great meaſure their Eſtates, whereby it hath
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105580:11"/>plainly ſhewed, That this is the Time and Seaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God is making known his Mighty Power, for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing and bringing under the Power of Darkneſs, that the Kingdoms of this World may become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of God; and that the Kingdom of his Son, which is in Righteouſneſs, Peace and Joy of his bleſſed holy Spirit may be ſet over all? And is not this according to that Prayer, <hi>Thy Kingdom come, thy Will be done on Earth, &amp;c?</hi> Now conſider, Are not all thoſe Wayes deſtructive to Mankind that are made up in the dark Conceivings of Man, without the Light of underſtanding the Will of God herein? And by your Works of Darkneſs, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the Bleſſed and Effectual Works of God's holy Spirit, what Miſery and Confuſion have you brought your ſelves and the Nations into, where you lie in Heaps in Controverſies about the Works and Words without, till the Enemy's works of Darkneſs be over-grown in you, by which you are ſo droven from the Preſence of God, and the Light of his Countenance, that you are greatly confounded, kicking and ſtumbling at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Stone, the which in your Fleſhly Worldly Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom you think too mean to be in your Buildings? by reaſon of which, how many Faſhions are your Buildings of? reeling and ſtaggering from one Faſhion to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſoaring aloft in your airy Imaginations of the things of God, in uſing your Wits and Arts to bend the Holy Men's Teſtimonies to your corrupt Wills and Affections: And ſo much more as you ſtrive in theſe Works, ſo much more you are and muſt be confounded: What a ſad Work have you herein taken in hand? and what vaſt Sums of Money have you exacted out of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to maintain the Pride and Arrogancy of your hearts herein?</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105580:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105580:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105580:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105580:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:105580:14"/>
            <p>Oh! that there were ſuch a Heart in people to ſit down before the Lord, that they may partake ſo much of his bleſſed Works as to open the Eye of their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, that they may ſee over theſe Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where nothing is good nor pleaſant to the truly Hungering and Thirſting Souls after God's Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: How miſerably have theſe Nations been cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe blind Guides, who have exacted abundance of Wages under Pretence of being Healers and Curers of the Nations; but are now found by the <hi>Effectual Workings</hi> of the Light of God's holy Spirit to be the chief Inſtruments of the letting in of Darkneſs, Corruption and Abominations that raign on the Earth; Through that Adulterated Spirit, the Mother of all Harlots, who are departed from the true Spouſe, and ſo running and hunting after others Bleſſed Works and Experiences, have ſet up Trades in their Arts of telling and boaſting of others Lines and Works, where that Adulterated Spirit hath covered them, who are corrupted with her Sorceries and VVitchcraft under various Faſhions of Confeſſions and Profeſſions of God and his Chriſt? But underneath theſe Coverings are the ſame wicked hands by which the Juſt hath ſuffered, and been rejected and ſet at nought in all Ages.</p>
            <p>And through the bleſſed VVorks of the Light of God's holy Spirit theſe Corrupt Workers and Works of Darkneſs being diſcovered, and a Righteous Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in Thouſands that ſtand againſt them; what a ſad work do theſe blind Leaders make to hide themſelves from the VVrath of the Lamb that is coming upon them, looking back to the ſeveral Traditions, Cuſtoms and Commands of Men, from whence they derive ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Eſtabliſhments upon many Fleſhly rotten Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105580:14"/>as <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Directory,</hi> of Man's, none of God's Foundation: Chriſt, God's Foundation, is a Pure, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Unſpotted Foundation, where God's Wiſdom and Counſel directs in and through the Works of his Holy Spirit, the which are perfect and good in every degree thereof, by which people are built up a Spiritual Houſe to the Honour and Praiſe in and through God's bleſſed Works forever.</p>
            <p>So to God's Covenant and Works muſt all Mankind be brought under (that are redeemed and made alive to God) therefore we deny the <hi>Presbyterian</hi>'s <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Directory,</hi> as being but a <hi>meer Parcel of Conceivings and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations,</hi> which tends to hide the Holy Covenant, and Foundation of the Righteous People in Generations paſt, and now preſent in being (who were and are built upon the ſure Foundation, which God hath laid, and thereon in Covenant with his Righteous Holy Works.)</p>
            <p>And concerning your Foundation, who are built upon a <hi>Church-Faith,</hi> made up by an Aſſembly of <hi>Diviners</hi> out of their own Brain, in their fleſhly Comprehenſions; its man's Works, full of Blemiſhes and Spots (and not God's) God's Foundation and Works thereon are Pure and Holy, without Spot, Wrinkles or Blemiſh. And foraſmuch as your made up Faith and Works tend to the making void the pretious Faith of God's Elect, which is the Gift of God, the which <hi>purifies the Heart, and works by Love, and giveth Victory over the Old World of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and Sin, without which Faith there is no pleaſing God:</hi> And ſo to this One Faith, One Baptiſm and One Lord Teſtimony is given, and againſt all feigned Faiths, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105580:15"/>Works of Men's Hands, the which are in Wickedneſs, by which the Juſt was ſlain.</p>
            <p>And concerning that Head of the Beaſt, which is branched out into ſeveral Horns in <hi>Feigned Humility</hi> and <hi>Will-Worſhip,</hi> intruding into things which they are not led into by the Light of God's holy Spirit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Foundation being not from a certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the immediate Works of God's holy bleſſed Spirit in them; But are in their own Willings and Run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings into Imaginations and Conceivings about the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the holy Men of God; but being out of their Spirit and Works therein, what dark Works of Plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Dippings in outward Water, and imaginary Fellowſhips in outward Elements; but being out of a true Senſe of the Works of God's Spirit, and its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration to enlighten them, and give them an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Times and Seaſons of the Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Works of the Mighty God; what Strangers are they to the New Birth, and the One Baptiſm of Chriſt with Fire and the Holy Spirit, to burn and conſume Luſts, and ſo to bring down every high Thought and vain Imaginations under his Feet, who is the Lamb of God that takes away the Sins of the World? And ſo by that One Pure Holy Spirit of God are many bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into one Body, where God's Will is done on Earth by him that abides forever. So not by the Works of Man's Righteouſneſs is any ſaved, but by the Merciful Works of God in his Son, by the VVaſhing of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and Renewing of the holy Spirit. So into this pure holy Name muſt all be Baptized, Dipped, Plunged, the which tends to the bringing out of all Falſe Fellowſhips, into that One and Only Pure Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>to walk in the Light of the Lord, where the Blood of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105580:15"/>Chriſt cleanſes from all Sin:</hi> A pure Baptiſm indeed, a pure Waſhing in a pure Fountain, where Filthineſs that is within man comes to be waſhed away, and thereby way is made for the Comfortable Freſh Springs that riſe from the Fountain of Love and Mercies (the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) of which many outward things are Shadows; but the Good Thing it ſelf is come, Glory to God on high (<hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.9, 10.) So to his bleſſed Works, who muſt increaſe, is Teſtimony given; and againſt all the Works of Men's Hands, the which tend to the making void thereof. So the Fountain of God ſtands ſure, and muſt do forever; and all Falſe Foundations, whereon People have built muſt be ſwept away for evermore.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THE bleſſed and unſpotted Foundation the Mighty God of Heaven and Earth hath laid, which is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the holy God;</hi> by the Light and Teaching of which Mankind comes to be inſpired with a right Underſtanding concerning things that differ; even that which is pretious and wholſome, ſo good for Food for every Soul; and that which is vile and filthy, which tends to the defiling and bringing Souls into Bondage. And ſo <hi>John</hi> in his 1 Epiſt. 2.20. ſaith unto the then Believers, who had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this heavenly Gift, <hi>But ye have an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction from the Holy One, and ye know all things:</hi> Herein was and is God's Love in his Son manifeſted to the World, to deſtroy his Works, who hath led Mankind into Darkneſs; and ſo through Man's Obedience in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and believing in theſe bleſſed and unſpotted Works of God in his Son, the Enmity comes to be ſlain, that ſeparates Mankind from God; and ſo the bleſſed Works of God in his Son, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling and bringing back them who have been loſt by wandering and roving in their own Willings and Runnings in this cloudy and dark Night, they come to be ſeen, felt and enjoyed by them who were and are Partakers thereof, even of God's Works in his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105580:16"/>Son, by which the Eye of the Underſtanding comes to be opened, and ſo the Offenſive Eye, that is offended at God's Works, comes to be put out: And thus the Light and Underſtanding of that pure Life comes to be known, the which hath been as a Lamb ſlain from the Foundation of the World of Wickedneſs by the Subtilty of the Serpent in Man's Heart.</p>
               <p>And now to the Praiſe and Honour of God Almighty, who hath drawn Thouſands by the Strivings of the Grace of his Holy Spirit to the Knowledge of his Way, Chriſt, the Truth, Way and Life, the which is without Spot and Blemiſh; the ſame Pure, Holy and Unchangeable Way and Foundation on which the holy Men of God were built in Ages and Generations paſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. and are built upon the Foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief Corner-Stone. So here was the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> Foundation, from whence proceeded and proceeds Heavenly, Bleſſed and Gratious Words, from the true Senſe and Feeling of the Operation and powerful Works of God's holy and bleſſed Spirit: And from this Holy, Uncorruptible, Pure Foundation and Way of God were all True Miniſters and Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of others raiſed, from the Bleſſed Operation of the Spirit of Truth in themſelves, whereby they had and have the Will and Mind of God unto People, though not all in the ſame Meaſure or Degree: But every one being faithful to his own Meaſure of Knowledge, is therein a Miniſter of the Univerſal Love of God in his Eternal Spirit unto the VVorld.</p>
               <p>So here lies the Difference between True Teaching and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, (and Falſe.) The True Teaching being the Anointing of God's Holy Spirit and Power, wherewith Mankind being anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and taught of God, and according to God's Bleſſed VVill therein, in a Croſs to his own Carnal VVill and Affections, ſpeaking forth and delivering the Truth unto people, as it is in Jeſus, Lord of all, in whom the Peace is, and from whom Peace is proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under thoſe Conditions and Quallifications as it pleaſes him to make and tender, who is Lord of all. The Falſe Teaching is that Spirit of Iniquity, the Old Deceiver of the VVorld, the Serpent that worked and wrought under a Myſtery, ſubjecting Mankind unto his VVill under a Vain Hope, through which he beguiled
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105580:16"/>him at firſt, drawing out a Compliance of his VVill unto his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, and ſo to tranſgreſs the bleſſed Commands of his Maker; through which yielding of Mankind unto the Serpent's Counſel, they became Tranſgreſſors of God's Holy Law and Covenant; and for that Cauſe was drove from God's Preſence, and then Fear entered; and Trouble and Sorrow entered by Man's yielding to the Traytor, by which means he partook of the Nature of his Curſed VVorks; and being thus drove out of the Garden of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> the Lord placed a Flaming Sword, which turned every way to keep the VVay of the Tree of Life.</p>
               <p>And now the ſame Myſtery of VVickedneſs, by which Mankind was drawn into Tranſgreſſion, the ſame ſpiritual VVickedneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got in a High Place, above the pure holy Seed of God in Man, there keeps Mankind in Bondage to his Will under many fair &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Hopes, <hi>That though Sin and Tranſgreſſion,</hi> the Cauſe of Death, <hi>be not finiſhed in them, yet Deliverance ſhall be had by the Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation and Works of the Seed without them,</hi> So here Mankind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Imbondaged by theſe Corruptible VVorks under the Dark Power of the Enemy, from whence ariſes all Corruptible VVays, Man being gone from the Uprightneſs in which he was created, goes now abroad hunting about in his Inventions and Conceivings, being led about by this Thieviſh Spirit, which firſt drew his Mind from the VVill of God, and ſo in this is climing up and down, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way but the right Door; and ſo being in this Earthly VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from below, by Arts and Trades ſet a teaching of their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations and Conceivings concerning the Holy VVorks without, and ſo here lay down Foundations under Confeſſions and Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Good VVorks and Gratious VVords without, and thereby keep the Serpent's works of Tranſgreſſion and Sin alive within; and here the falſe Teachers under ſeveral Covers of Confeſſions and Profeſſions in the ſpirit of Antichriſt ſet up. And ſo here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing toſſed up and down with Floods of Inventions, from thence their Shameful VVorks are caſt up in the Old VVorld of Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and Sin, where theſe Falſe Teachers are ſo rivited, the works of the Enemy being become ſo natural unto them by reaſon of the Continuance of Time in Tranſgreſſion and Sin, that thereby they are now become impudent and bold, even to dare to plead for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105580:17"/>the Serpent's works, Sin, for term of Life; taking it for Deluſion and high Preſumption for any to ſpeak to the contrary: And ſo here Falſe Teachers being raiſed from the works of the Enemy, moving in the Earthly VViſdom for Earthly Things, being propt and bolſtered up through Vain Glory, Praiſe of Men and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Pounds, many Nobles and ſpecial Marks, with abundance of Crowns and frequent Appearances of Angels; in and by which they are ſo oyled, that their Tongues run at their own VVills and Luſts, by fair Speeches of other Men's Lines and VVorks; with which ignorant Simple People being taken, have ſo fed and oyled the VVheeles of theſe Tradeſ-men, the which hath ſet them up ſo ſtrong, that they make all the Defence they can to ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Clients in the old VVorld of Sin and Iniquity: And ſo theſe Falſe Teachers having put Darkneſs for Light, and Light for Darkneſs, what ſtrong Pillars and Props they are grown under the Devil's Kingdom and Power of Darkneſs, under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heads more that might be mentioned, being derived from one Beaſtly Power, from whence is riſen ſeveral Heads, and ſo bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out into ſeveral Horns, the which are puſhing every way againſt the Horn of God's Anointing (the Power and Strength of the Effectual and Bleſſed Teachings of his Holy and Bleſſed Spirit) the Door and VVay by which all muſt enter that come to be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied with God's Righteouſneſs (Chriſt) the ſame Seed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in the beginning to <hi>bruiſe the Serpent's Head;</hi> the effectual VVorks and Power of which, according to God's good Pleaſure, was and is manifeſt in the VVorld. So to the Praiſe and Honour of God's Holy VVorks many can ſay, <hi>Peace from him that is, and was, and is to come, Jeſus, Lord of all, who delivers his People from their Sins, the Lamb of God that takes away the Sins of the World;</hi> through which Powerful and Bleſſed VVorks Mercy and Peace is extended to all Mankind, without Reſpect of Perſons, upon Earth.</p>
               <p>So Bleſſed are they that Fear God, and are found out of their own VVillings and Runnings in their perverſe and crooked Nature, in a true Submiſſion and Obedience to the Righteous VVorks of God's Righteous Holy Spirit, the true <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Spirit, that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105580:17"/>may flouriſh again, and that <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> and <hi>Paganiſm</hi> under that Name <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may be ſubdued, and vaniſh away; and Jeſus, Lord of all, exalted in the Hearts and Minds of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple over all his Enemies: Then ſhall the Nations flouriſh, and yield Fruit in Seaſon, to the Praiſe and Honour of God forever.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd now all you Merchants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Howl, and cry, <hi>Alas, alas! What! all theſe pretious Trades, whereby we have gotten ſo much Gain, muſt they all Down? Where be all our Mountains and Rocks, that have been ſo long a making up by all our Fellow-Tradeſ-Men by Arts and Inventions, in Profeſſions and Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Good Works and Works without through Ages and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations paſt? Will none of theſe Mountains and Rocks cover and hide us from the great Wrath of the Lamb? What muſt we now bow to his Righteous Works who takes away the Sins of the World? or elſe will he grant us No Peace? Alas, Alas! What Clothing in Scarlet, and Purple, and Fine Linnen of</hi> Egypt, <hi>with pretious Stones, will theſe no longer hide our Sins and Iniquities? Muſt all our Works herein, wherein we thought to have eſtabliſhed our own Righteouſneſs, muſt they now all be put off as Dung and Droſs? Alas! Alas! Though we have lived ſo far from the Knowledge of the Operation and Works of God's Holy Spirit, as utterly to deny its Revelations now adayes, and ſo have been Dark, and void of the Knowledge of God's Righteous Chaſtiſments, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes therein; yet we have preſumed, that by Cuſtom of Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Profeſſions of God's Good Works, done in and through Holy Men without us, would have given us a Right to his Holineſs, though the Luſt of the Eye, the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Pride of Life and Friendſhip of the World had never been whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubdued in us, but in ſuch a part as might he conſiſtent with our Gain and Profit in the World. But Alas! Alas! Our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings be too narrow, they will no longer hide us; God's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Works are abroad in the Earth, who is inſpiring his People with True Light of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; and</hi> Mordecai <hi>ſits in the Gate, and will not bow to Wickedneſs</hi> (Haman) <hi>Alas! Alas! We have twined and twiſted about through many Crafts and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105580:18"/>ſome of our beſt Arts-Men having called the Light a</hi> Devil, <hi>ſome others a</hi> Natural Light, <hi>and others a</hi> Bewildering Light; <hi>and likewiſe many Falſe Accuſations have we raiſed, with Evil Reports, Scornings and Reproachings of the People called</hi> Quakers, <hi>for Confeſſing to the Works of the Light of God's Holy Spirit; yet all our Shifts do not at all help us, but thoſe Works proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and they are generally a Faithful People to their Teſtimony. Alas! Alas! Who would have thought our Mother had been ſuch a Harlot? What delicate Inchantments and Sorceries hath ſhe uſed and trained us up in, that we have been thus deceived, and thereby have been Inſtruments of deceiving the whole Nations? Alas! Alas! We can flee into no Corner nor Hole but we are found out and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued. Alas! Alas! can't all the Wiſdom of the VVorld, and Arts therein help to hide our Sins and Iniquities from the Light of the Lamb? Is every Creature ſo clearly manifeſt in his Sight, that made all things good in the beginning? And is he now as work again? And muſt all yield to his VVorks, or be accounted his Enemies, and be caſt out of his Preſence, who is Lord of all, whoſe is the Earth and the Fulneſs thereof? Alas! Alas! VVords of Repentance of Sin will not ſerve now; there muſt be a true Repentance and Forſaking Sin and Evil, or elſe we periſh forever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Even ſo it muſt be done to you Workers of Iniquity, who have been and are as Props and Pillars, ſtrengthening the Old World of Tranſgreſſion in Sin and Iniquity, the Devil's works, and therein withſtood the Sufficiency of God's Love manifeſted to the World in his Son to deſtroy the Devil's works, which works of Tranſgreſſion the old ſubtil Serpent, the Deceiver of the Nations, in and through his Inſtruments is ſtriving and labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to maintain under ſeveral and very large and ſpecious Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of crying out, <hi>Lord, Lord:</hi> But come Workers of Iniquity, theſe Good Words will not give you Admittance into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God; its not they that ſay, <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> ſhall enter therein; but they that do the Will of God: And was not his Will manifeſted to the World in his Son, that they that believed and followed him in doing his Father's Will might not Periſh, but have everlaſting Life? And do not many of you confeſs to this in words? who ſay in your ſet Prayers, <hi>That we may follow the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105580:18"/>of Chriſt's great Humiliation and Patience, that we may attain to his Reſurrection, &amp;c.</hi> VVhat brave VVords have you VVorkers of Iniquity got in your Old Bottle, that can hold none of the New VVine? And ſo in your corrupt VVills what will the uſing good VVords do you good, but thereby add to your Condemnation, who by Good VVords and corrupt and Bad Actions are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and have withſtood the Good-will, Pleaſure and Love of God in his Son to the VVorld. So your works of Darkneſs and Falſhood are clearly manifeſted, and you can't hide them from the Light: But the Light of the Effectual and Powerful VVorks of God's holy Spirit, wherein his VVill is manifeſt, is riſing more and more, to a more perfect Day of his VVill being done upon Earth, to the Praiſe and Honour of his bleſſed and holy Name, whoſe VVorks are Pure, Holy, Juſt and Perfect in every degree thereof, and tend to the true Reformation, Peace, Proſperity and Eſtabliſhment of all Mankind in God's Love and Mercy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in forever.</p>
               <p>So worſhipped be God that made Heaven and Earth, and the Fountains of VVaters, and all things therein, who fills the hearts of the Upright with Joy and Gladneſs, through the Shinings forth of the Light of his Countenance, who ſits upon his Throne and ſaith, <hi>Behold I make all things New</hi> (Amen.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105580:19"/>
               <p>AND now unto ſuch who are in Doubt, <hi>Whether God's Holy Spirit doth ſo effectually work now adayes as in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Times.</hi> Unto you I ſay, What Fleſh could ever have indured ſuch grievous and continued Puniſhments in Tryals of divers ſorts, by Impriſouments, and Baniſhments, and Hangings, and Killings, as in <hi>New-England</hi> (and Impriſonments to Death and Spoiling of Goods) in Old <hi>England,</hi> and Cruel Mockings, and Scoffings and Bloodſhed by Unmerciful Men? Indeed ſome in a Voluntary Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility have ſomewhat appeared in Sufferings, but being in their own Willillings and Runnings and VVorks therein, how have they been overcome, their Strength being an Arm of Fleſh, as well as others, and ſo Fleſhly VVorks have been overcome by Fleſhly VVorks? But its not ſo with them who are in Scorn and Deriſion called <hi>Quakers,</hi> becauſe they have bowed to God's VVay, the which is quite different to Man's wayes, was that Name given; but in God's VVay hath his Arm been revealed, and its Strength made manifeſt in our VVeakneſs: So that to the Praiſe of him that lives forever the Operation of his Bleſſed Spirit is felt, as in the Primitive Dayes; and the Glory and Comfort of it hath mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred Strength and Refreſhment in the time of Tryals; though this Way of God's Proceeding hath been hid from the vulterous evil Eye. So to the Praiſe and Glory of God is Confeſſion made through the Operation of his holy Spirit, through which Thouſands have been preſerved and kept from bowing to the ſeed of <hi>Cain, Haman</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> which hath made the World as a <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> where wild Fruits and wild Actions ſpring. So we can truly ſay to the Praiſe of God, Let not the Wiſe Men in the Wiſdom of this World glory in their Wiſdom, nor the Strong Men in their Strength, nor the Mighty Men in their Might; but let all wait in that pure Meaſure of the Light of God's Spirit in their Conſciences, that by it they may draw near unto God, that they may know his Bleſſed Works of Mercy, and Love, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Earth, wherein that true Glory and Honour of God is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105580:19"/>
               <p>ANd further, Concerning <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> this I ſay; As the Bleſſed Works of the Light of God's holy Spirit has place in Hearts, and ſo opens Underſtandings, a Diſcovery will be made from thence of the Falſe, Corrupt and Wicked Miniſters, who open their Mouthes for Gifts and Rewards, from whoſe Works in fair and deceitful Speeches Prophaneneſs is gone out into the World, where the Revelations of God's holy Spirit is denyed and ſet at nought; they telling People, <hi>Revelations are ceaſed, they are not to be known now adayes, &amp;c.</hi> So the Sight of all the Good and Bleſſed Works of God's Good and Holy Spirit are become as a Sealed Book, ſo that they who have exalted their Parts and Knowledge in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> above the pure Life of Jeſus, they can't read in it, becauſe it is ſealed; and theſe Learned Men (Unlearned in the Things of God) can't read in it, becauſe they draw near to God with their Mouthes, and ſeem to Honour him with their Lips, but their Hearts not being Right in his Sight, therefore are their VViſdoms confounded, and Underſtanding in the Things of God kept from them.</p>
               <p>So its ſuch who have nothing to miniſter from but a Divination of their own Brain, in Conceivings and Imaginations concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Works of God in others, but from no Knowledge of his Works in themſelves; ſo they run and Divine for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and Gifts and Rewards in that adulterated whoriſh Spirit, which hath ſate a long time, and reigned over People, who have been as unſtable and unſettled as Waters, reeling and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering to and fro through the Sorceries and Witchcraft of that whoriſh wicked ſpirit, into which Cup the Kings of the Earth have drunk, and been made drunk with Envy, Malice and Hatred one againſt another; and from Luſts, which have been conceived in that Wicked and untimely Womb, have proceeded VVars, and Fightings, and Hatred one againſt another, and alſo Hatred againſt the Appearance of God's good VVorks in others.</p>
               <p>So its againſt that bad and wicked ſpirit, which is not to ſpeak in the Church, that I am moved to give Teſtimony in and through the Operation of God's good and holy Spirit, the which is mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105580:20"/>at work this Day, wherein his Power is made manifeſt to deſtroy the Devil's works, and ſo a VVay making for the Pouring forth of God's Holy and Bleſſed Spirit more and more upon all Fleſh; from whence I believe there are at preſent Hundreds of Able and Gifted Miniſters in this Nation, in ſome Degree or Meaſure or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God's Holy Spirit, who can ſpeak experimentally of what they have felt, handled, taſted and ſeen of his VVorks therein, who is the <hi>Beginning and Ending of every Good and Perfect Work and Gift in and for them who wait to know his VVill and do it:</hi> And through theſe Bleſſed Works muſt the Wounded and Deſtracted Nations be healed and ſet to rights; and all that hinder theſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Works of God's Holy and Unlimited Spirit, they are Enemies to God, and to their own Souls, and to the Nation and Country where they live.</p>
               <p>So to that of God in every ones Conſcience I appeal in theſe weighty and high Concerns, wherein I having done the Will of God, I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>A Lover of the Truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſeek the Good of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,</hi> Stephen Smith.</signed> 
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The 9th Day of the 4th Moneth, 1673.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105580:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>NOW unto you who will ſay, <hi>I writ out of Enmity:</hi> Therein you ſay true; for in the true Enmity, which God hath put between the two Seeds, viz. <hi>The Bleſſed Seed of the VVoman,</hi> and <hi>The Curſed Seed of the Serpent:</hi> So that in that which is truly good, that bleſſed Seed by which Evil is overcome, according to the Good-will of God, in that I give Teſtimony againſt that which is Corruptible and Bad, by which Mankind is led away into Darkneſs, and there captivated under the Enemy's Power.</p>
               <p>But if any ſhall ſay, <hi>I wiſh herein any Ill to any one's Perſon:</hi> I do ſay in the Truth and Uprightneſs of my Heart, That ſuch do falſly accuſe me; For I know, in the Bleſſed Seed Interceſſion is made through me and many Thouſands, that Light may riſe in them who ſit in Darkneſs, that the Cauſe of Enmity againſt the bleſſed Seed may be ſlain; and that Mankind, who are dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins, may be quickened, and raiſed into the Glorious Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Liberty in the Son of God, where we may live together in Peace with God and one with another, to the Praiſe and Glory of his Holy Name forever.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Stephen Smith.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
